<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christians preparation to the worthy receiuing of the blessed sacrament of the Lords Supper</title>
            <author>Field, Theophilus, 1574-1636.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 47 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00731</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10860</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118349</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853556</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853556</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18943</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00731)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18943)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 885:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christians preparation to the worthy receiuing of the blessed sacrament of the Lords Supper</title>
                  <author>Field, Theophilus, 1574-1636.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 87, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Augustine Mathewes for Tho. Thorp,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication to the Duchess of Lennox signed: "Theoph. Landauensis", i.e. Theophilus Field.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A preparation to the Sacrament.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Sion College. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Lord's Supper --  Meditations.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18943:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18943:1"/>
            <p>A CHRISTIANS PREPARATION TO THE WORTHY Receiuing of the Bleſſed <hi>Sacrament of the</hi> Lords Supper.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nunquam ſatis dicitur,</l>
               <l>quod nunquam ſatis diſcitur.</l>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Augustine Mathewes,</hi> for <hi>Tho. Thorp.</hi> 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18943:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18943:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT High and Illuſtrious La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the Lady FRAVNCIS, Dutcheſſe of Leonox, Counteſſe of Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt excellent Lady.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſpeciall grace your Grace did mee, when not long ſince, you were pleaſed to Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of the Bleſſed Sacrament, hath em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldened mee (hauing euer ſithence ſtudied
<pb facs="tcp:18943:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> how to ſhew my ſelfe thankefull) to inuite your Ladiſhip to the reading of this my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe (A Chriſtians preparation to the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Receiuing of the Lords Supper) which I moſt humbly preſent, in hope of good accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, at leaſt of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, as comming from</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Graces moſt deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted daily Beadſman.</hi> Theoph. Landauenſis.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:18943:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hriſtian Reader: when this ſmall <hi>Trac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate</hi> was <hi>firſt</hi> written by the <hi>Reuerend Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour,</hi> it was intended onely for the <hi>priuate vſe</hi> of a <hi>Noble Friend</hi> of his; and not for <hi>publique Cognizance.</hi> But the <hi>Copie</hi> thereof being communicated to certaine <hi>High</hi> and <hi>Honourable Perſonages, They</hi> were very earneſt with <hi>Him,</hi> to haue it committed to the Preſſe <hi>His Medeſtie</hi> holding it vnworthy any Eſtimation at all, was very loath to venture it to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Deſtiny of Bookes, <hi>Cenſure.</hi> Which when I (being <hi>one</hi> whom he vouchſafeth to deſcend ſo low
<pb facs="tcp:18943:4"/> as to call <hi>Friend)</hi> did vnderſtand, I made bold to entreat the peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of it: and <hi>afterwards,</hi> hauing by inceſſant importunitie, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned <hi>His</hi> too much <hi>baſhfulneſſe,</hi> I extorted from him, at the laſt, a <hi>Permiſſion</hi> to publiſh it. For how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I knew that diuers <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>Godly Diuines</hi> had written vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>ſame Subiect,</hi> &amp; that eating too much <hi>Manna,</hi> hath made the world <hi>ſicke</hi> of a <hi>Surfeit;</hi> yet I was perſwaded, that ſome of the <hi>Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> ſort of people might reape ſome ghoſtly comfort and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by <hi>This,</hi> as well as <hi>Others</hi> of <hi>higheſt Ranke</hi> had done before. And <hi>further,</hi> conſidering with my ſelfe his <hi>Maiesties late gracious, wiſe, and godly Directions to the Clergie, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Catechiſing;</hi> I thought that <hi>this ſmall Treatiſe</hi> agreeing and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting with thoſe <hi>Directions,</hi> and treating of one <hi>Branch</hi> of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme, might prooue not <hi>alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</hi> vn-vſefull to any. <hi>Much</hi> I will not ſay in Commendation of it: but thus much I may; and thou
<pb facs="tcp:18943:4"/> alſo wilt (if neither <hi>Ignorance</hi> doe blind, nor <hi>Preiudice</hi> hood-winke the eye of thy Iudgement) boldly and truly affirme; That it ſauoreth not either of the <hi>Superſtition</hi> of the <hi>One,</hi> or <hi>Baſtard</hi> and <hi>phantaſticke No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueltie</hi> of the <hi>Other Abberration</hi> in Religion: but ſpeaketh the ſame <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>Orthodox Doctrin</hi> (though not in the ſame Syllables) that is compriſed in the <hi>Articles,</hi> the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies</hi> and <hi>Catechiſme</hi> of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> And thoſe are <hi>our Rule</hi> to direct all our <hi>Inſtructions</hi> by, in this <hi>kinde.</hi> Thus wiſhing thee <hi>as much</hi> ghoſtly <hi>Benefit</hi> by it, as the <hi>Authour</hi> did to that <hi>Religious and Noble Perſonage,</hi> whoſe <hi>Pious</hi> deſire did firſt ſet him on work to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it, I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine, and the Authors Friend in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:18943:5"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap> not <hi>Life</hi> to <hi>All.</hi> For to ſome it is <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Deſtruction.</hi> For, <hi>He that eateth and drinketh vnworthily, eateth and drinketh</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. 11. 29.</note> 
               <hi>his owne damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>'Tis very ſtrange, that <hi>ſo Contrary</hi> effects, (as Life and Death) ſhould ſpring out of <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſelfe ſame Cauſe. Doth a Fountaine ſend out at</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iames 3. 11.</note> 
               <hi>one place bitter water and ſweet,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Iames?</hi> That may not be granted. And yet the ſame <hi>Sacrament</hi> of Chriſt his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Body and Blood, <hi>Mors est malis, vita Bonis,</hi> as <hi>Aquinas</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In Hymno.</note> ſpeaketh; It is <hi>Death to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked &amp; vnworthy, and Life to the godly and worthy Receiuer.</hi> But, Certainely, theſe two <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> effects doe not <hi>Naturally</hi> proceed from the Sacrament <hi>it ſelfe:</hi> but the <hi>One, (viz.</hi> Death) is cauſed by <hi>It,</hi> no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18943:5"/> then <hi>accidentally,</hi> and <hi>improperly.</hi> For the Sacrament it ſelfe was ordayned by Chriſt, to be an <hi>Inſtrument of ſpirituall Life;</hi> and no cauſe of <hi>Death</hi> or <hi>Damnation</hi> at all. But wee haue a <hi>common</hi> ſaying in the Schooles, That <hi>Omnis cauſa agit ſecundum diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem Subiecti;</hi> Euery cauſe doth worke according as the <hi>Subiect,</hi> (which it is to worke vpon) is fitted and diſpoſed. Therefore <hi>Experience</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that <hi>one</hi> and the <hi>ſame Heate</hi> of the <hi>ſame</hi> Sunne, doth <hi>Harden</hi> the Clay, and <hi>melt,</hi> or <hi>mollifie</hi> the Waxe. The <hi>ſame meat,</hi> doth nouriſh and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then an <hi>heathfull</hi> and <hi>ſound</hi> body; which, if it be eaten by perſons of <hi>ſicke</hi> and <hi>corrupted</hi> ſtomachs, doth but increaſe their Diſeaſe, and degenerate
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18943:6"/> into the malignant humour of the <hi>ſickneſſe</hi> it ſelfe. So, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer the Sacrament of the Lords body doth <hi>augment grace</hi> in the <hi>prepared heart</hi> of a <hi>poenitent Receiuer:</hi> yet the <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent</hi> and <hi>obſtinate</hi> ſinner, by partaking of that holy myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, becomes more ſicke in Soule, and more crazed in Conſcience, then before. <hi>That</hi> happeneth to him <hi>in Soule,</hi> which is reported to haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falne <note place="margin">Sabellicus lib. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>Emperour in his body; Cui in hoſtiâ conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tâ venenum attulit interitum,</hi> Who was poyſoned by recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the conſecrated Hoaſt. The Arke of the Couenant receiued into the houſe of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Edom</hi> (for the ſpace of three moneths) brought great benefits, and much happineſſe with it. <hi>For the Lord bleſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:18943:6"/> Obed. Edom, <hi>and all his houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 6. 10.</note> Yet for all that, the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims</hi> had the ſame Arke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, for a much lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger time; and they were ſo far from reaping any benefite or benediction by it, that the Lord powred his curſes and plagues vpon them, <hi>for detei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it.</hi> The reaſon of which different effects, was the <hi>Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> and <hi>Diſsimilitude</hi> of the <hi>Lodging</hi> or <hi>Roome</hi> into which the Arke was receiued. <hi>Obed-Edom</hi> entertained it with all humble reuerence, and pious deuotion of a ſanctified heart: The Philiſtims receiued it ſo <hi>indeuoutly</hi> and <hi>vnreuerently,</hi> that they forbare not to place it by their <hi>Idol Dagon.</hi> So this <note place="margin">1 Sam. 5. 2.</note> heauenly Sacrament becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>Death to the bad, and Life to the good:</hi> by reaſon of the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:18943:7"/> diuers Diſpoſition, and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent preparation of thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons which are partakers of it. <hi>Some</hi> 
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>like <hi>Obed-Edom)</hi> prepare their Soules before hand, to receiue it with <hi>Faith, Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, Humilitie,</hi> and <hi>Reuerence: Others</hi> (like the <hi>Philistims)</hi> make no ſuch reckoning of it, but receiue it <hi>hand ouer head,</hi> into an impenitent, an vnſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, &amp; an vnprepared heart; an heart <hi>wedded</hi> to wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and doe place it among their <hi>deare</hi> and <hi>darling</hi> ſinnes; which they <hi>doat</hi> vpon, &amp; <hi>adore</hi> no leſſe, then if they were their <hi>Idols.</hi> That therefore we may knowe <hi>How</hi> to receiue this food of our ſoules in ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as it may bring <hi>Life,</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> and <hi>Saluation</hi> to vs, the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſetteth vs downe the way, in his firſt <hi>Epistle</hi> to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18943:7"/> 
               <hi>Corinths,</hi> the 11. <hi>Chapter,</hi> at the 28. <hi>verſe. Let a man therefore examine himſelfe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which words of the bleſſed Apoſtle containe a <hi>Double charge:</hi> Firſt, that <hi>wee trie</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee eate; and ſecondly, that <hi>wee eate</hi> after triall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Before</hi> wee doe Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, the Apoſtle requires <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> of our ſelues: and then, <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Triall and Examination,</hi> hee commaunds vs to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate. And ſo hee encounters with <hi>two ſorts</hi> of men; wherof the <hi>One</hi> eats of this Bread, and <hi>Tries not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and thoſe offend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>firſt part.</hi> The <hi>Other</hi> trie themſelues; but <hi>doe not eat</hi> of <hi>this Bread:</hi> and theſe faile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>the ſecond.</hi> The firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyneth a <hi>Preparation,</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond a <hi>Participation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt, wee may conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18943:8"/> two things:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
<list>
                     <item>Examining, 1. <hi>Euery man.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Examined: <hi>himſelfe.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. Parts.
<list>
                     <item>Maner
<list>
                           <item>of exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                     <item>Matter</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. The perſon that is to <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine,</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> render <hi>Quiſque,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Boet. Leitur.</note> euery Man. This dutie then is layd vpon euery one, bee hee ſubiect, or ſoueraigne Prieſt, or of the people. Which ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation ouer-turneth the <hi>Implicite Faith</hi> of the Romiſh Church. For euery <hi>Lay-man</hi> and <hi>woman</hi> ought to turne <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor,</hi> and <hi>Examiner,</hi> and to be endued with ſufficient know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge for this heauenly Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. He muſt looke not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly through the <hi>Spectacles</hi> of the Prieſt, but alſo ſee with
<pb facs="tcp:18943:8"/> his <hi>owne Eyes,</hi> and bee able to Trie himſelfe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The perſon that <hi>Euery</hi> man is bound to <hi>try</hi> and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, is <hi>Himſelfe:</hi> that is, his owne perſon, not the perſons of other men: for a man to ſet vp his Conſiſtory in the Conſcences of others, is <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaical pride</hi> and preſumption. We muſt not bee buſie <hi>Biſhops in other mens Dioceſſes,</hi> but <note place="margin">1 Pet. 4. 15. 1 Theſ. 4. 11.</note> 
               <hi>meddle with our owne buſineſſe.</hi> We muſt not <hi>break</hi> our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours <hi>head</hi> with the <hi>Phariſee; (God I thank thee, I am not like other men, &amp;c. nor like this Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lican)</hi> but ſmite our <hi>own breſts,</hi> with the <hi>Publican;</hi> and ſay, <hi>O God be mercifull to mee a ſinner.</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> complained of men in his time, that they were <hi>Curioſi ad cognoſcendum vita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alienam, deſidioſi ad corri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendam</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:18943:9"/> 
               <hi>ſuam:</hi> and Reuerend <hi>Hooker</hi> ſayeth of men in <hi>our Time,</hi> That their <hi>Vertue is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but gladly to heare the reproofe of others vices.</hi> And herein they are not vnfitly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled to <hi>Taylors</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers;</hi> whereof the one doth <hi>Meaſure,</hi> and the other doth <hi>Trim</hi> all others, except <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</hi> But our Sauiour Chriſt would not haue vs to trouble our ſelues about the <hi>Mote in our Brothers Eye,</hi> but rather to <note place="margin">Math. 7.</note> 
               <hi>pull out the beame that is in our owne eye.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> in this place, chargeth vs not to <hi>prie</hi> into the liues of others, but to trie and examine our owne ſelues.</p>
            <p>Leauing therefore the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <hi>Examining</hi> and <hi>Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned;</hi> we come to the <hi>Parts</hi> of Examination; and they are
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18943:9"/> 
               <hi>Two: One,</hi> concerning the <hi>Manner;</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Matter</hi> of our Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Manner of our Exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> conſiſteth in <hi>theſe two:</hi> Namely, that it be made, firſt <hi>Vprightly;</hi> ſecondly, <hi>Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, it is required, that in examining <hi>our conſciences,</hi> wee deale <hi>vprightly,</hi> faithfully, and ſincerely with God. For ſo much is implyed in the word (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) Examine: which commands a diligent and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row ſearch, and an <hi>earneſt and exact</hi> enquiry; ſuch as <hi>Lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries</hi> and <hi>Gold-ſmiths</hi> vſe, to finde out <hi>True</hi> Mettall from <hi>Counterfeit.</hi> The <hi>fraudulencie</hi> of mans heart is vnſearchable by any on earth, ſaue by the <hi>Spirit</hi> and <hi>Conſcience</hi> of a mans
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18943:10"/> owne ſelfe. <hi>Wee our ſelues</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. 2. 11.</note> therefore are to call <hi>our ſelues</hi> to examination before our owne Conſciences, which wil either <hi>accuſe vs,</hi> or <hi>excuſe vs,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom 2. 15.</note> in the things that wee haue done. If our <hi>Heart,</hi> or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience doe <hi>condemne</hi> vs, <hi>God is greater then our heart, and knoweth all things;</hi> but if <hi>our heart condemne vs not,</hi> then <note place="margin">1 Iohn 3. 21. 22.</note> 
               <hi>haue we boldneſſe towards God.</hi> We are therefore to examine our ſelues <hi>with a ſincere Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> not ſeeking to <hi>diſſemble</hi> or excuſe any maner of ſinne, bee it <hi>neuer ſo deare</hi> vnto vs; Leaſt, in ſo doing, we doe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>prouoke</hi> the Lord to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, then <hi>appeaſe</hi> his wrath. One ſaith, that <hi>Conſcientia eſt ſcientia cum ſcientiâ; Scientia nostra cum Scientiâ Dei congru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens:</hi> a <hi>Knowledge</hi> in vs agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18943:10"/> with <hi>another Knowledge</hi> which is in <hi>God.</hi> In which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard, <hi>ſome</hi> haue compared the <hi>Conſcience</hi> to a <hi>Tally.</hi> Bakers and Brewers (&amp; ſuch <hi>Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> as vſe to deliuer their commodities to their Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers <hi>vpon Tale)</hi> are wont to <hi>cleaue a ſticke</hi> in Two, and to giue to their Cuſtomers the <hi>one ſide</hi> of it, keeping <hi>the other</hi> to themſelues; and <hi>euer,</hi> as they deliuer out their wares, they make a <hi>certaine number of Markes</hi> and <hi>Nickes</hi> vpon both parts of their <hi>Tallies,</hi> to keepe euen reckonings: So that if either goe about to deceiue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they neede but to drawe out <hi>Their ſide of the Tally,</hi> and <hi>That</hi> will ſoone diſcouer the Truth. Euery action which we doe, be <hi>it good or badd,</hi> is markt and <hi>nickt</hi> vpon the <hi>Tally</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18943:11"/> of our <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>Gods Science:</hi> if wee haue laboured to <hi>deface</hi> or <hi>ſcrape</hi> out any thing that hath beene marked on <hi>our ſide</hi> of the Tally; God needes but to drawe out <hi>that</hi> which is <hi>markt on his ſide,</hi> and <hi>That</hi> will ſoone conuince vs of falſehood. <hi>For God is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then our heart:</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſtandes vs in hand to deale <hi>Truely,</hi> and vprightly with him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, examination muſt be made, not onely <hi>Vprightly,</hi> but alſo <hi>Neceſſarily:</hi> and <hi>This</hi> wee may gather out of the word <hi>(Therefore.) Whoſoeuer ſhall eate this Bread, and drinke this Cup of the Lord vnworthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſhalbe guilty of the Body and Blood of the Lord. Therefore</hi> let a man examine, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Triall of our ſelues then is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18943:11"/> neceſſary, both in reſpect of the <hi>dutie enioyned,</hi> and of the <hi>Danger</hi> if wee neglect that dutie.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of <hi>our dutie:</hi> For Chriſt in his firſt Inſtitution, vſed a <hi>commaunding.</hi> Tearme: <hi>Doe This.</hi> Doe this in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance <hi>of Mee.</hi> So that it is <note place="margin">Luke 22. 19.</note> 
               <hi>not</hi> in our choyce to <hi>Doe it,</hi> or <hi>not to</hi> doe it. If any be not <hi>fit,</hi> he muſt endeuour to <hi>make</hi> him ſelfe fit: and the <hi>way</hi> to make him fit, is <hi>Examination. Let a man therefore examine himſelfe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Triall is <hi>neceſſary</hi> in regard of the <hi>Danger,</hi> if we receiue the Lords Body <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The danger is in reſpect of the ſinne: verſe 27. <hi>Hee is guiltie of the Body and Blood of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:18943:12"/> 2. The <hi>puniſhment</hi> for ſinne.</p>
            <p>Which <hi>puniſhment</hi> is <hi>two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold: Generall:</hi> verſe 29. <hi>Hee eateth and drinketh his owne damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Particular,</hi> verſe 30. <hi>For this cauſe many are weake, and ſicke, and die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the <hi>Manner</hi> of our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, <note place="margin">Id. Ibid.</note> we proceed to the <hi>Matters,</hi> concerning which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Communicant muſt bee Tryed, and they are ſummari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Two,</hi> viz. <hi>Repentance,</hi> and <hi>Faith.</hi> Theſe two are like <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> his Twinnes: they go together hand in hand: For there is no <hi>True repentance</hi> without a liuely faith; nor a <hi>liuely faith</hi> without true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
            <p>Wee attaine to <hi>Repentance,</hi> by the <hi>ſight</hi> and <hi>knowledge</hi> of our <hi>Sinnes.</hi> Our <hi>ſinnes</hi> are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18943:12"/> and <hi>made knowen</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs by the <hi>Law</hi> of God. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſinne is as a <hi>ſpot</hi> or <hi>ſtaine</hi> vpon the Soule; and the <hi>Law</hi> of God is a <hi>Looking-glaſſe</hi> of the Soule, which ſheweth eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpot and wrinckle. It is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoouefull <note place="margin">Iam. 1. 21.</note> then for euery one to ſet <hi>this Glaſſe</hi> before him, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sacra Scriptura, quaſi ſpeculum quoddam, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis oc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lis obiici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: ibi pulchra noſtra in Chriſto proſpicimus, ibi foeda noſtra in nobis cernimus.</hi> Bernard in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralib.</note> and according <hi>to it,</hi> to examin the <hi>beautie</hi> or <hi>deformitie</hi> of his Soule. The ſumme of this <hi>Law of God</hi> is compriſed in the <hi>Decalogue,</hi> or <hi>Ten Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Which Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments are diuided into <hi>Two Tables.</hi> The <hi>Firſt,</hi> containing the duties which we <hi>owe vnto God:</hi> The <hi>Second,</hi> the duties which we <hi>owe vnto our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</hi> The <hi>Firſt,</hi> commandeth all manner of <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> that we owe to God: the ſecond commaundeth <hi>Righteouſnes</hi> to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18943:13"/> our Neighbour.</p>
            <p>The Commandements con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the <hi>firſt Table</hi> are foure. The firſt wherof is this.</p>
            <div n="1" type="commandment">
               <head>1. COMMANDEMENT.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt haue none other Gods but mee.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The <hi>Duties</hi> commaunded in theſe wordes, are principally ſeuen.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The acknowledging of the true God, as hee hath <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed himſelfe</hi> in his Word.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To <hi>feare</hi> him more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To <hi>loue</hi> him aboue all creatures in heauen and earth.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To put all our <hi>Confidence</hi> and truſt in him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. To <hi>humble</hi> our ſelues be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</p>
               <p n="6">6. To bee <hi>patient,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with what he is pleaſed to ſend, or lay vpon vs.</p>
               <p n="7">7. To <hi>Hope</hi> in him onely.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:18943:13"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>Sinnes forbidden</hi> in this com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement are:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Ignorance</hi> of the true God, <hi>falſe opinions</hi> touching the <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Col. 3. 5. Epheſ. 5. 5. Philip. 3. 8.</note> and <hi>will</hi> of God, <hi>Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition, Idolatrie, Trusting</hi> in Creatures.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Carnall</hi> ſecuritie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of God.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Hating</hi> of God, or a <hi>coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit</hi> loue of him: all <hi>inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> loue of ones ſelfe, or of other creatures.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Hypocriticall truſt</hi> in God; <hi>ſtaggering,</hi> and <hi>diffidence</hi> in the goodnes and power of God: <hi>Confidence</hi> in the <hi>helpe</hi> of man.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Pride, Arrogance, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit humilitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>Impatience,</hi> or murmuring againſt God.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Deſperation,</hi> and <hi>Preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="commandment">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:18943:14"/>
               <head>2. COMMANDEMENT.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any grauen Image, to bewe downe to it, to worſhip it.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The <hi>Dutie</hi> commanded, is,</p>
               <p>To giue vnto God <hi>all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward religious worſhip</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> as in the firſt Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, wee are inioyned to <hi>Honour him in our heart</hi> aboue all.</p>
               <p>The maine ſinnes forbidden are.</p>
               <p n="1">1. To <hi>adore with the Body,</hi> (in a religious manner) any <hi>Image</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom 1. 23. Exod. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1. Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> made with mans hands, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee of <hi>Saint</hi> or <hi>Angel,</hi> or <hi>any</hi> creature.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To <hi>deuiſe</hi> any <hi>bodily</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, which hee hath <note place="margin">Coloſſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 18</note> not reuealed, and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, either plainely, or by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction and implicitly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="commandment">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18943:14"/>
               <head>3. COMMANDEMENT.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt not take the Name of the Lord thy God in vaine.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The <hi>Duties</hi> commaunded are:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Due honour &amp; reuerence to the <hi>Name</hi> of God. <note place="margin">Pſal. 50. 15. Ioel 2. 12. Iohn 16. 23. Heb. 1. 6. Pſal. 147. 7. Mat. 10. 13.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. <hi>Innocation</hi> and Prayer.</item>
                  <item>3. <hi>Thankſgiuing.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. <hi>Confeſsion,</hi> and publication of Gods praiſes.</item>
                  <item>5. The <hi>glorifying</hi> of his name <note place="margin">Pſal. 34. 4.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>6. <hi>Swearing lawfully</hi> by the <note place="margin">Deut 6. 13. &amp; 10. 20.</note> name of God.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The <hi>Sinnes</hi> forbidden are:</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Want of Reuerence</hi> to the Name of God; <hi>neglect of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, Innocation, Thankſgiuing, Confeſsion, Praiſe,</hi> and <hi>Glorify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2 All <hi>Railing, Banning, Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, Blaſphemies, Maledictions, Imprecations,</hi> wherin the name of God is vſed &amp; prophaned.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:18943:15"/> 3 All <hi>for ſwearing, falſe ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Leuit. 19. 12. Math. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 34. Pſal. 15. 3. Iam. 5. 12</note> 
                  <hi>light</hi> &amp; <hi>common ſwearing:</hi> all <hi>fooliſh calling</hi> of God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, all <hi>raſh</hi> vowes.</p>
               <p n="4">4 All <hi>Enchantments, Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafts,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Leuit. 29. 6. Deut. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Sooth ſayings, Diuinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Exorciſings,</hi> and other <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicall Superstitions,</hi> which are <note place="margin">1 Sam. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 7.</note> made by <hi>Wizards</hi> out of the Scripture for the moſt part.</p>
               <p n="5">5 All <hi>wiles, deceits, couſenages</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iere 14. 15. Epheſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> and <hi>lyes,</hi> broached vnder <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence</hi> of the <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Word</hi> of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="commandment">
               <head>4. COMMANDEMENT.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt keepe holy the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath day.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Duties</hi> commanded are.</p>
               <p n="1">1 A religious worſhipping <note place="margin">Pſal. 92. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</note> of God <hi>in publike,</hi> in the <hi>great Congregation,</hi> which is nothing elſe but our doing <hi>of Seruice to God</hi> in <hi>Common Prayer</hi> and <note place="margin">Heb. 10. 25.</note>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:18943:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Thankſgiuing</hi> in the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 An <hi>attentiue</hi> hearing and <note place="margin">Actes 13. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 1 Cor. 14. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>meditating</hi> of Gods <hi>works,</hi> and his <hi>word</hi> preached.</p>
               <p n="3">3 A <hi>frequent vſe</hi> of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 20. Actes 20. 7.</note> Sacraments.</p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Deeds of piety</hi> to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance <note place="margin">1 Cor. 16. 1. Galat. 6. 6.</note> of the <hi>Miniſters</hi> of Chriſt, and <hi>Almeſdeeds</hi> to the <hi>Poore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>Charitable offices</hi> to our <hi>Neighbours,</hi> in <hi>comforting</hi> the <hi>afflicted, viſiting</hi> the <hi>ſicke, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 A <hi>ſquaring</hi> of our owne <note place="margin">Titus 2. 10. Rom. 2. 24.</note> liues and manners according to <hi>right</hi> Chriſtianitie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sinnes</hi> forbidden are.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Abſenting</hi> our ſelues <hi>wilfully</hi> from the <hi>Church,</hi> vpon <hi>Sundays</hi> and other <hi>Holydayes:</hi> or (being preſent) not to <hi>regard</hi> the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice</hi> that wee ought to tender there to God in <hi>publique;</hi> but to come onely to heare a <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:18943:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> which is but an <hi>Inferiour end</hi> of comming to Church vpon Holy dayes, wherin <hi>God</hi> doth rather <hi>ſerue</hi> vs, then <hi>wee</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 92. Heb. 10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.</note> 
                  <hi>ſerue</hi> God.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Contemning</hi> of the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery</hi> of the Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or any kind of <hi>Abuſe</hi> of the ſame.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Neglecting</hi> to <hi>heare</hi> or <hi>read</hi> the Scriptures, <hi>intermiſsion</hi> of <hi>Prayers, deeds</hi> of <hi>pietie, Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Charity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Intermedling</hi> with <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, prophane,</hi> and <hi>ordinary af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fayres</hi> on thoſe dayes.</p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>Bibbings, feaſtings, Reuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, Dancings,</hi> and <hi>Sportings,</hi> to the <hi>hinderance</hi> of our deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſeruice of God.</p>
               <trailer>So much for the <hi>firſt Table.</hi> The <hi>ſecond Table</hi> reſpects our <hi>Neighbour:</hi> and it conteineth ſixe Commandements; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18943:16"/> the <hi>firſt,</hi> commandeth vs to doe our <hi>Neighbour all the good wee can:</hi> the <hi>other</hi> charge vs to doe him <hi>no manner of hurt.</hi>
               </trailer>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="commandment">
               <head>5. COMMANDEMENT.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Honour thy Father and thy Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>This Commandement teacheth the duties of <hi>Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors</hi> to their <hi>Inferiours:</hi> and of all <hi>Inferiors</hi> to their <hi>Superiors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Duties of <hi>Superiors</hi> to their <hi>Inferiors</hi> are.</p>
               <p>Firſt, to embrace them with a <hi>Fatherly</hi> affection.</p>
               <p>Secondly, as much, as in vs lyeth, to <hi>prouide</hi> for their <hi>maintenance</hi> and <hi>education.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, to <hi>defend</hi> them from wrong and violence.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, to <hi>inſtruct</hi> them <note place="margin">Ephe. 6. 4.</note> in the <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>nurture</hi> of the Lord.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:18943:17"/>
               <p> Fiftly, to giue <hi>good example</hi> vnto them by our owne <hi>reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious</hi> and <hi>honeſt</hi> carriage.</p>
               <p>Sixtly, to <hi>chaſtiſe</hi> and <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect</hi> them for their offences.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Duties</hi> of <hi>Inferiours</hi> to <hi>Superiours</hi> are:</p>
               <p>Firſt, to ſhew all <hi>ſiliall loue</hi> vnto them.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to <hi>honour</hi> them inwardly, in <hi>Heart,</hi> by a reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent eſtimation of them; and <hi>outwardly,</hi> in <hi>word and geſture,</hi> by bowing to them, and ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king <hi>ſubmiſſely</hi> and humbly to them.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to yeeld all <hi>wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling obedience</hi> to their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, <hi>ſo long as they are not croſſe to Gods Commandements.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, to <hi>imitate</hi> their vertuous life and religious conuerſation.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, in <hi>word and deed</hi> to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:18943:17"/> expreſſe our <hi>Thankefulneſſe</hi> vnto them.</p>
               <p>Sixtly to <hi>winke</hi> at their <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections</hi> and to <hi>beare</hi> with their <hi>infirmities.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Sinns</hi> forbidden <hi>both parties</hi> are:</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>want of naturall</hi> affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and all <hi>impiety</hi> towards any, to whom wee owe loue and reuerence.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Euery <hi>Neglect</hi> of dutie, or an <hi>hypocriticall fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of</hi> the ſame.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Too much <hi>Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,</hi> or <hi>ouer-fondneſſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Contempt, Scorne, Stubburnnes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fiftly, <hi>Ingratitude.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixtly, Too much <hi>rigour, ſeueritie, roughneſſe,</hi> or <hi>harſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> of behauiour.</p>
               <p>Seuenthly, <hi>Lightneſſe, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſtie, Boaſting.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="commandment">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:18943:18"/>
               <head>6 COMMANDEMENT.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt not kill.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The <hi>Sinnes</hi> heere forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den are:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Firſt, all manner of <hi>hurt</hi> or <note place="margin">Exod. 21. 24. Num. 25. 7.</note> violence done to the <hi>perſon</hi> of our neighbour.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, <hi>Anger, Hatred,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 1 Ioſ. 3. 15. Gal. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Rom 1. 29. Phil. 2. 14. 16. 13. 5. 2 Cor. 12. 24. Mat. 5. 22. Rom. 1. 30. Gal. 5. 15. Rom 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>Euill-will, Ranckor, deſire of Reuenge.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Thirdly, <hi>Waywardneſſe, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>humanity, Wrathfull lookes.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Fourthly, <hi>Rayſing, Ill words Inſulting, Prouocations</hi> to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</item>
                  <item>Fiftly, <hi>Treachery, Crueltie.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <p>The <hi>Duties</hi> commanded are:</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Humanitie,</hi> and an <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faigned</hi> loue of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Beneuolence,</hi> or well-wiſhing to his perſon
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18943:18"/> from a <hi>compaſsionate</hi> heart.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>Meekeneſſe,</hi> and <hi>long ſuffering, patiently bearing</hi> and <hi>willingly forgiuing</hi> iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <hi>Affabilitie, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſſe,</hi> and all kind of <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous behauiour.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="commandment">
               <head>7 COMMANDEMEMT.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt not commit Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The <hi>Sins</hi> forbidden are:</p>
               <p>Firſt, all <hi>Lustings</hi> and <hi>Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>in the heart</hi> after the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall company of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>Immodesty,</hi> the <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 14. Prou. 7. 13. Eſay 3.</note> 
                  <hi>wanton Eye,</hi> the <hi>Whoriſh</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, <hi>Mincing gate, Gariſh at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Loue-ſongs, filthy</hi> and <hi>baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Col. 3. 8. Ephe. 4. 29</note> 
                  <hi>talking.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 All manner of <hi>vncleane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 32.</note>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:18943:19"/> whether it be with a <hi>ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle</hi> perſon, or with a <hi>marryed</hi> perſon, and <hi>how elſe ſoeuer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Duties</hi> commanded, are:</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Chaſtity</hi> of Body &amp; mind, <note place="margin">Ores, eaſta, legas, ieiunes, otia vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes: Si ſeruare voles corpora caſta Deo.</note> whether it bee in the ſtate of <hi>Virginitie, Marriage,</hi> or <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowhood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Modesty,</hi> adorning our <hi>thoughts, wordes, deeds, gesture, countenance, attyre, gate, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Moderation,</hi> and <hi>Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> in meate, drinke, ſleepe, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="commandment">
               <head>8. COMMANDEMENT.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt not Steale.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sinnes</hi> forbidden are.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The <hi>inward greedineſſe of the heart,</hi> longing after <hi>wealth,</hi> howſoeuer to be gotten; <hi>Aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, coueting other mens</hi> riches.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:18943:19"/> 2 All <hi>Fraude, guile, deceit,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Leuit. 19. 11. Amos 8. 5, 6. Deut. 25. 1 Theſſ. 4. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>trickes, quirkes,</hi> all <hi>impoſtures</hi> in bargaines, and contracts, and <hi>ſelling</hi> of <hi>counterfeit</hi> wares.</p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Vſury,</hi> and <hi>Extortion,</hi> or <note place="margin">Mich. 3. Ex. 22. Pro. 22. Ezech. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Oppreſsion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Theft, Robbery, Sacriledge, Couzning</hi> of the Country or <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Thom.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>q.</hi> 66. Iob 24. 9.</note> Common-weale, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="5">5 <hi>Idleneſſe.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ezech. 16.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6 <hi>Nigardiſe</hi> and <hi>Profuſion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Duties</hi> commanded are:</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Iuſtitia commutatiua,</hi> Iuſt <note place="margin">Prou. 5. 16. Rom. 12. 13.</note> and <hi>vpright dealing,</hi> in getting, in buying, and ſelling.</p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Care</hi> to <hi>ſaue</hi> our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour from <hi>Dammage: Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence</hi> in doing the workes of our <hi>Calling.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Liberalitie.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Hebr. 13. 1 Tim. 6. 17.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4 <hi>Frugalitie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="commandment">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:18943:20"/>
               <head>9. COMMANDEMENT.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt not beare falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sinnes</hi> forbidden are. <note place="margin">Exod. 233. Pſal. 101. Iob 29. Leuit. 19. 15.</note>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>1 All manner of <hi>Lying,</hi> and <hi>falſe teſtimonies.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Pratling, habling, ſcurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 1 Cor. 5. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>ſlaundering, defaming,</hi> and <hi>backbiting.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 Siniſter <hi>ſuſpition, raſh</hi> and <note place="margin">Mat. 15. 19. 1 Cor. 13. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>wrongful iudging</hi> of our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Duties</hi> commanded are.</p>
               <p n="1">1 Sincere and <hi>plaine meaning</hi> and <hi>ſpeaking.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>Taciturnitie, graue ſpeach,</hi> and a <hi>Moderate vſe</hi> of the <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Ioſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 14.</note> tongue.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Bearing of a <hi>Good Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> of our Neighbour, and iudging all things to <hi>the best.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="commandment">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:18943:20"/>
               <head>10. COMMANDEMENT.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Thou ſhalt not couet.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>The <hi>former Commandements</hi> doe forbid the <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>deſires</hi> of the heart, as well as the <hi>outward Act and Practiſe.</hi> For God is a <hi>Spirit, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt bee worſhipped in the Spirit.</hi> But the <hi>former</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements did condemne <hi>ſetled thought</hi> to do miſchiefe: But <hi>this</hi> condemneth euen the very <hi>firſt inclination and motion to ſinne,</hi> though a man doe <hi>ne-neuer conſent,</hi> but <hi>ſnubb</hi> it in the <note place="margin">Rom. 7. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>beginning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>neglect of doing</hi> what we are commanded, is a <hi>Sin</hi> of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>doing</hi> of that which we are <hi>forbidden,</hi> is a <hi>Sin</hi> of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If therefore wee ſhall exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18943:21"/> the <hi>face</hi> of our <hi>Soules,</hi> by this <hi>Looking-glaſſe of Gods law,</hi> we ſhall find it ſtrangely <hi>defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> with ſpots and ſtaynes: nay, much <hi>defaced</hi> with byles, vlcers, and wounds; which cannot chuſe but worke in our hearts a great <hi>griefe</hi> &amp; <hi>ſorrow:</hi> eſpecially, if wee conſider <hi>first</hi> the <hi>party againſt whom</hi> euery ſinne (which the <hi>Law</hi> chargeth vs withall) is either <hi>immediatly</hi> or <hi>mediatly</hi> committed: And <hi>ſecondly,</hi> if we ſhall duly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what <hi>puniſhment</hi> wee make our ſelues lyable vnto by eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſin, whether it bee of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion, or omiſsion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First,</hi> the <hi>party diſhonoured</hi> and offended by our ſinnes is the <hi>moſt mightie God,</hi> who <hi>made</hi> our bodies and ſoules, to the end, that wee with them, might (not <hi>diſhonour</hi> him by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18943:21"/> breaking his law) but doe him <hi>all ſeruice</hi> and <hi>honour.</hi> In <hi>him</hi> wee muſt conſider <hi>theſe three things</hi> ſpecially: firſt, his <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> and <hi>Knowledge:</hi> ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, his <hi>Iuſtice:</hi> thirdly, his <hi>Power.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 His <hi>Wiſedome</hi> is <hi>ſuch,</hi> that no <hi>thing,</hi> no <hi>action,</hi> or <hi>cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> that paſſeth from vs, is hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den from it: <hi>Thou ſpieſt out all my wayes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob.</hi> And <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>Thou knoweſt all my</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 139. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>thoughts long before they doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 His <hi>Iuſtice</hi> is ſo <hi>ſtrickt</hi> and <hi>ſeuere,</hi> that (without <hi>full ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction)</hi> it will not ſuffer one <hi>Sin</hi> to ſcape <hi>vnpuniſhed.</hi> The wicked <hi>Angels</hi> ſinned but <hi>once;</hi> and yet for <hi>that one</hi> ſinne, hee hath reſerued them in <hi>euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting chaines vnder darkneſſe, to</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iude ver. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>the iudgement of the great day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:18943:22"/> 3 His <hi>Power</hi> is <hi>infinite.</hi> The <hi>King,</hi> by his <hi>power,</hi> may for <hi>Treaſon,</hi> or other crimes cauſe a mans <hi>body</hi> to bee tortured, tormented, and deſtroyed: but <hi>God</hi> can caſt <hi>body and ſoule</hi> into <hi>hell fire:</hi> and <hi>all the Kings</hi> on earth, and <hi>Angels</hi> in heauen are not able to fetch them backe againe. In the <hi>very act</hi> of thy ſinne, he is of power <hi>to deſtroy both</hi> thy body and ſoule in a <hi>moment,</hi> and to <hi>ſnatch thee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, ſo that there ſhall be none to deliuer thee.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal 50. laſt.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Then in the <hi>ſecond place,</hi> doe but conſider what <hi>puniſhment</hi> we are to expect for euery ſin; that is, <hi>eternall death</hi> and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of body and ſoule in hell fire. <hi>The wages of Sin is</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 6. laſt.</note> 
                  <hi>death:</hi> a <hi>thouſand</hi> ſinns, a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand deaths. And ſurely (mee thinkes) wee cannot chuſe but
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18943:22"/> haue <hi>ſorrow.</hi> Sorrow of <hi>Attriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> at the leaſt, if not ſorrow of <hi>Contrition.</hi> Sorrow of <hi>attrition</hi> is when we grieue for <hi>feare</hi> of puniſhment. Sorrow of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition,</hi> is when we grieue <hi>for ſinne,</hi> as it is ſin, that is, as it is <hi>a diſhonoring</hi> of God: the <hi>lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> is the <hi>better ſorrow</hi> of the two. And yet the <hi>ſorrow of Attrition</hi> is not to bee <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended,</hi> or refuſed; becauſe it is a <hi>meanes</hi> to bring vs to the <hi>true godly ſorrow,</hi> or ſorrow of Contrition. Whereby we do ſorrow for <hi>nothing ſo</hi> much, as for that <hi>by our ſinnes</hi> wee haue <hi>loſt the fauor</hi> of God, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of his Spirit.</p>
               <p>And this <hi>godly ſorrow,</hi> will <hi>worke in vs repentance, not to bee</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>repented of.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Some men,</hi> in this caſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, are <hi>much</hi> miſtaken:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18943:23"/> For <hi>generally,</hi> the world imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that <hi>Repentance</hi> is no thing elſe but a <hi>godly ſorrow for ſin,</hi> and a <hi>turning</hi> or conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from <hi>Sin</hi> to <hi>God.</hi> But S. <hi>Paul</hi> had <hi>ſtudied the caſe</hi> tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly, and <hi>He</hi> teacheth vs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. <hi>viz.</hi> That <hi>Repentance</hi> is a great deale <hi>different</hi> from <hi>godly ſorrow:</hi> for godly ſorrow (ſaith he) cauſeth <hi>Repentance</hi> ſo that <hi>Repentance</hi> is an <hi>effect</hi> or <hi>fruite</hi> of godly ſorrow; and godly ſorrow is <hi>the cauſe</hi> of repentance: ſo that <hi>Sorrow</hi> and <hi>Repentance</hi> are not the <hi>ſame.</hi> For <hi>Nihil est cauſà ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſius.</hi> Nothing is cauſe of it ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Secondly, ſome take it to be no more but <hi>Conuerſion;</hi> that is, a <hi>leauing off</hi> to ſinne, and a <hi>turning to God.</hi> But Conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is an <hi>Antecedent</hi> of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:18943:23"/> and Repentance is a <hi>conſequent of Conuerſion,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Ieremie</hi> teacheth. Surely, <hi>after that I conuerted,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ierem. 31. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>then I repented.</hi> So that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion <hi>goeth before</hi> Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and Repentance <hi>follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after</hi> Conuerſion.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells vs, that <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance</hi> is <hi>another</hi> manner of matter; and conſiſts of <hi>ſeuen parts:</hi> An Inuentory <hi>whereof</hi> he deliuereth vnto vs: For, <hi>behold this godly ſorrow, what great</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor 7. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>carefulneſſe it hath wrought in you?</hi> yea, <hi>what Apologie, or defenſe?</hi> yea, <hi>what indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on?</hi> yea, <hi>what feare?</hi> yea, <hi>what earneſt deſire?</hi> yea, <hi>what emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation?</hi> yea, <hi>what reuenge, or puniſhment?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are the ſeuen parts of the <hi>body of true Repentance;</hi> and acording to <hi>theſe</hi> ſeuen, we are
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18943:24"/> to examine our Conſciences. For true repentance requireth the <hi>whole man;</hi> that is, the <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding</hi> part, the <hi>Affections,</hi> and the <hi>Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 The <hi>vnderſtanding</hi> part muſt ſhew it ſelfe in <hi>Careful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> and <hi>Apologie.</hi> 2 The <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> are to bee exerciſed in <hi>Indignation, Feare, Deſire,</hi> and <hi>Emulation.</hi> 3. The <hi>Body,</hi> in <hi>Reuenge,</hi> or <hi>Puniſhment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>First</hi> then, to make our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance <hi>ſound,</hi> it is required that wee bee <hi>carefull</hi> to auoyd ſinnes to come, and to do with diligence, the works that God commands vs.</p>
               <p>This is the firſt part of the Body of Repentance, and it pertaines to the <hi>Superiour part</hi> of the Soule, the <hi>Vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> and is a part of <hi>Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:18943:24"/> 2 The <hi>ſecond Act</hi> of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance which belongeth to the <hi>vnderſtanding part,</hi> is <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logie,</hi> or <hi>Defence.</hi> Where the <hi>Apostles meaning</hi> is not, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man ſhould make an <hi>Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, for his ſins</hi> (for <hi>he that hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth or excuſeth his ſins ſhall not proſper, ſaith Solomon,)</hi> but that euery good Chriſtian ſhould be able to make a <hi>iuſt Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> for the <hi>Truth and Sincerity</hi> of his godly ſorrow for his ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="2">2 The <hi>vpper part of the Soule</hi> (1. the vnderſtanding) is char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with thoſe <hi>two actions.</hi> But the <hi>lower part</hi> of the Soule (in matter of repentance) is char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged with <hi>foure Affections,</hi> viz. 1. <hi>Indignation;</hi> 2. <hi>Feare;</hi> 3 <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire;</hi> 4. <hi>Emulation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Indignation,</hi> hath reſpect to <hi>Sinnes paſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Feare,</hi> is in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:18943:25"/> of <hi>Sins to come.</hi> 3. <hi>Deſire,</hi> hath an Eye to <hi>good things.</hi> 4. <hi>Emulation,</hi> hath a reference to <hi>good Perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Indignation</hi> hath the <hi>firſt place;</hi> becauſe it is an Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Anger,</hi> moſt properly belonging to Repentance. <hi>Carefulneſſe</hi> is a part of <hi>Proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi> But <hi>Repentance,</hi> prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, is a part of <hi>Iustice vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catiue,</hi> and to <hi>vindicatiue Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice,</hi> no <hi>affection</hi> ſo agreeable, as <hi>Anger and Indignation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Wee are then to conceiue <hi>Anger againſt our ſelues</hi> for our ſinnes; and <hi>euery Anger</hi> will not ſerue the turne: but it muſt be an <hi>high kind of</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, <hi>Indignation.</hi> Now indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation preſuppoſeth an <hi>indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> done. By our ſinnes wee offer <hi>indignity to God,</hi> and to our <hi>owne Soules;</hi> and therefore
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:18943:25"/> we are to conceiue great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation againſt our ſelues for committing <hi>ſuch indigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> againſt ſo <hi>good</hi> and ſo <hi>great</hi> a Maieſtie.</p>
               <p n="4">4 The <hi>fourth</hi> part of our Repentance muſt bee an <hi>holy Feare</hi> (in regard of the <hi>Time to come)</hi> to fall into any ſin.</p>
               <p n="5">5 The <hi>fifth</hi> is an <hi>earneſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire</hi> to pleaſe God in all things, and to doe euery <hi>good dutie</hi> which he commandeth in his Law.</p>
               <p n="6">6 The <hi>ſixth</hi> is an <hi>holy emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Gods perſons:</hi> in ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to <hi>match</hi> them in graces and vertues; and if it bee poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, to <hi>ouer-match</hi> them.</p>
               <p n="7">7 The <hi>ſeuenth</hi> thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, is <hi>Reuenge</hi> or <hi>Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> which is the very <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection</hi> and complement <hi>of Repentance:</hi> without <hi>which</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:18943:26"/> 
                  <hi>Reuenge, non agitur ſed fingi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur poenitentia,</hi> our repentance is no repentance, but <hi>hypocriſie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The only way to <hi>eſcape the Iudgement</hi> of God in another world, is to <hi>ſit in iudgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our ſelues</hi> in this world, to giue <hi>ſentence</hi> againſt our ſelues for our offences: ſo Saint Paul teacheth. <hi>If wee</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>would iudge our ſelues we ſhould not bee iudged of the Lord.</hi> But after <hi>iudging</hi> of our ſelues, and <hi>giuing ſentence</hi> againſt our ſelues, wee muſt ſtreight pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed <hi>to execution,</hi> and <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of our ſelues for our ſins: <hi>for ſo</hi> we ſhall eſcape <hi>Eternall puniſhment</hi> in another world. For <hi>Non erit gemina afflictio</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Nahum</hi> ſpeaketh, God will not <hi>puniſh twiſe</hi> for the ſame offence. So that to <note n="d" place="margin">Wee muſt ioyne Reuenge of our ſelues, with Iudging of our ſelues. 1 Cor. 11. 31.</note> 
                  <hi>Indicare</hi> we muſt neceſſarily
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:18943:26"/> ioyne <hi>Vindicare,</hi> and ſo take <hi>vengeance</hi> of our ſelues for our <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 11.</note> ſinnes <hi>here,</hi> that we <hi>may eſcape</hi> the eternal vengeance of God in Hell-fire.</p>
               <p>Now the Fathers, <hi>ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelues vpon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> haue diſtinguiſhed ſins into <hi>theſe three kinds,</hi> viz. <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall, Carnall,</hi> &amp; <hi>worldly.</hi> Sins of the <hi>Soule,</hi> Sinnes of the <hi>Fleſh,</hi> Sinnes of the <hi>World.</hi> And there is <hi>in Scripture</hi> a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall puniſhment ſet downe, for euery <hi>ſeuerall kinde</hi> of theſe Sinnes.</p>
               <p n="1">1 The Soule hath two parts, <hi>Superiour, and Inferiour.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Superiour</hi> Sins perteining to this, are <hi>Pride, contempt of God, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 Sins of the <hi>Inferiour</hi> Ira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcible part, are <hi>wrath, deſire</hi> of <hi>reuenge</hi> for wrongs done.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:18943:27"/> 2 Luſting after vanities.</p>
               <p>The Soule, is a <hi>fliting thing,</hi> neuer at reſt; but euer rouing abroad thorow a thouſand <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires:</hi> the way to <hi>puniſh</hi> it, is to call it <hi>home,</hi> and to force it to <hi>ſettle</hi> vpon ſome <hi>vnpleaſing</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect: as to <hi>call to remembrance</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 38.</note> the yeeres of our life fore paſt in <hi>Amaritudine animae:</hi> to tye it, to thinke vpon <hi>Death,</hi> and <hi>Iudgement,</hi> &amp; Hell, which will ſoone pull downe the pride of it. The <hi>Iraſcible part,</hi> we muſt puniſh, by ſtudying to be <hi>quiet</hi> and <hi>patient,</hi> to put vp wrongs, and be ready to forgiue. The <hi>Luſting part</hi> is to be puniſhed, by ſetting our affections and <hi>Desires</hi> on good things, or things that are aboue.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Sinnes <hi>of the fleſh,</hi> are, <hi>Vncleanneſſe, Drunkenneſſe, Gluttony, eaſe, ſleepe, &amp;c.</hi> For
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:18943:27"/> 
                  <hi>theſe,</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Caſtigo corpus,</hi> I beate <hi>downe my body,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 25.</note> and bring it in ſubiection. The <hi>Body</hi> deſires to <hi>fare well</hi> in meats and drinkes: This wee muſt puniſh by <hi>faſting,</hi> either <note n="a" place="margin">From all ſuſtenance, as Dauid. 2. Sam. 12. 17. Exod. 10. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>à toto;</hi> or if <hi>that</hi> we cannot do, yet <note n="b" place="margin">From ſuch a quantitie, and but only <hi>guſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</hi> Acts 10. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>à tanto:</hi> If that our <hi>health</hi> will not permit that, yet to faſt, <note n="c" place="margin">From ſuch kind of meates, as Dan. 10. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>à tali,</hi> from <hi>dainties,</hi> and incentiues to ſinne. The <hi>Body</hi> deſireth <hi>Eaſe,</hi> to lye ſoft and richly, in beds of <hi>Downe,</hi> and <hi>Iuory.</hi> This wee muſt puniſh <note place="margin">1 Sam. 12.</note> with <hi>Dauid,</hi> by <hi>lying hard,</hi> as vpon the bare ground, &amp;c. The <hi>Body</hi> deſireth <hi>Sleepe in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe: This</hi> muſt bee puniſhed with <hi>watching:</hi> or if wee bee not able to watch <hi>all night,</hi> yet as Chriſt ſaith to <hi>Peter,</hi> Wee <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 40.</note> muſt <hi>force</hi> our ſelues to watch <hi>one houre</hi> with Chriſt: and <hi>that houre</hi> is to be ſpent in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18943:28"/> 
                  <hi>Meditations,</hi> in <hi>Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Deuotion</hi> to God. 2. The <hi>Fleſh</hi> deſireth to enioy a <hi>beautifull</hi> perſon: <hi>This</hi> muſt bee puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by making a <hi>Couenant</hi> with our eyes, <hi>not to thinke vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iob 37. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>a woman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>Worldly</hi> Sinnes, are <hi>Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, Ambition, Thirst after</hi> the <hi>outward</hi> commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the World. And <hi>theſe</hi> muſt be puniſhed <hi>by the Purſe:</hi> Firſt, by making <hi>reſtitution</hi> of whatſoeuer wee haue gotten <hi>contrarie</hi> to the law of God. Secondly, by being <hi>bountifull</hi> in deeds of <hi>Piety, to the Prieſts of God,</hi> and the Miniſters of the Goſpell. Thirdly, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>liberall</hi> in deeds of <hi>mercy</hi> to the <hi>poore</hi> members of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe <hi>euery one</hi> is not of Iudgment to know the <hi>right Quantum</hi> of all theſe <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:18943:28"/> to repentance; how much hee muſt take of each: therefore hee is to reſort to ſome <hi>vnderſtanding Priest;</hi> who is to preſcribe <hi>how much,</hi> or <hi>how little</hi> will ſerue the turne; for ſo the <hi>people did in the Old Teſtament,</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul takes vpon him to doe it in the New:</hi> for hee preſcribes a <hi>Sufficit</hi> to the <hi>incestuous Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Cor. 2. 6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But here we are to take heed of a <hi>Common error,</hi> which poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth the moſt men of <hi>theſe times:</hi> For <hi>many</hi> are perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that <hi>Repentance</hi> may bee performed in a <hi>moment of time.</hi> But they are <hi>groſſely deceiued:</hi> for <hi>all theſe</hi> ſeuen forenamed duties cannot bee done in a moment, but require ſome <hi>good ſpace</hi> of time. Therefore God ſaith, <hi>Dedi illi tempus ad</hi>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:18943:29"/> 
                  <hi>poenitendum, I gaue her a ſpace and time to repent in.</hi> And as <note place="margin">Apoc. 2. 21.</note> there muſt bee <hi>a ſpace</hi> to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the grace of Repentance in; ſo there muſt bee a <hi>certaine place</hi> aſſigned to it: for <hi>euery place</hi> is not fit for this exerciſe. And therefore the Prophet <hi>Zachary</hi> would haue vs to <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Zachar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> our ſelues from company, when we goe about to ſet our ſelues in the ſtate of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. And Saint <hi>Peter</hi> did put it in practiſe in his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; for he <hi>went out</hi> from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany <hi>firſt,</hi> and <hi>then</hi> wept bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly. <note place="margin">Math. 26. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> And hee deliuereth the ſame in doctrine. The Lord <hi>would haue no man to periſh,</hi> but <note place="margin">2. Peter 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>would haue men</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate themſelues to repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I haue ſtaied the longer vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this point; becauſe as there is <hi>no ſaluation</hi> without Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18943:29"/> ſo there can be no <hi>profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table acceſſe</hi> to the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble without it. But the Law is not onely a <hi>Looking-glaſſe,</hi> but alſo our <hi>Schoolemaſter</hi> to bring <note place="margin">Galat. 3. 24.</note> vs to Chriſt, to the Goſpell.</p>
               <p>Therefore I proceed now to the <hi>Second matter,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning which wee are to make our Examination, and that is <hi>Faith,</hi> and it conſiſteth of two things; <hi>Knowledge,</hi> and <hi>Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching Knowledge; eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <note place="margin">Knowledge.</note> Communicant is bound to know three <hi>generall poynts</hi> of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe,</hi> (as alſo the <hi>Summe</hi> of all, which <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are <hi>bound to beleeue)</hi> are contained in the <hi>Creed;</hi> which conſiſteth of three generall parts. The firſt part whereof concerneth <hi>God the Father;</hi> the ſecond, <hi>God the</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:18943:30"/> 
                  <hi>Sonne;</hi> the third, <hi>God the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Maine part</hi> of the Creed <note place="margin">Of Chriſt.</note> is that which concerneth <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Wherein I am taught to beleeue <hi>with my heart,</hi> That Ieſus Chriſt is <hi>very God,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten of the <hi>Father</hi> from all eternitie, <hi>before all worlds;</hi> and the <hi>ſame</hi> Chriſt is <hi>True Man,</hi> borne of <hi>Mary</hi> the Virgine: This <hi>God-man,</hi> and <hi>Man God,</hi> is my <hi>Lord,</hi> who (when I was vtterly periſhed and damned) <hi>redeemed</hi> mee from <hi>Death,</hi> and from the <hi>power of Sathan;</hi> not with <hi>Golde</hi> or <hi>Siluer;</hi> but with his owne holy and <hi>precious Blood,</hi> and by his <hi>vndeſerued Death</hi> &amp; <hi>Paſsion:</hi> that <hi>I</hi> might be <hi>His owne,</hi> and might liue in his <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and ſerue <hi>Him</hi> without <hi>ſeruile feare,</hi> in perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall holineſſe, &amp; righteouſnes
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18943:30"/> of life; euen as he <hi>roſe</hi> from the <hi>dead,</hi> and now <hi>liueth</hi> and raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth for euer. I beleeue that there is no <hi>Saluation</hi> but <hi>by him onely;</hi> no <hi>fruition</hi> of God, but <hi>through him.</hi> He purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saluation and Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>not for me onely, but for the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Iohn 2. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>whole world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the <hi>Benefit</hi> of Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">Of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> is an <hi>vniuerſall benefit,</hi> and belongeth to <hi>all Mankinde;</hi> yet <hi>all mankind</hi> are not <hi>partakers</hi> of it. <hi>None</hi> doe <hi>(ordinarily)</hi> pertake of it, but ſuch as haue it paſſed vnto them <hi>vnder Seale.</hi> The <hi>Seales</hi> which God vſeth to <hi>apply vnto mee</hi> in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, that which Chriſt wrought for <hi>all the world</hi> in generall, are the <hi>Two Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: Baptiſme,</hi> and the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi> of Chriſtes Body and Blood. And <hi>heere</hi> comes in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18943:31"/> the <hi>neceſsitie</hi> of Faith, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Sacraments: for <hi>they</hi> are <hi>both</hi> of them, <hi>Sacramenta Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>i,</hi> Sacraments of Faith: <hi>ſo called</hi> by the Fathers; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Myſteries</hi> in them contained, are <hi>not</hi> to be <hi>iudged</hi> by our <hi>Senſes,</hi> nor <hi>diſcuſſed</hi> by <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but to bee <hi>apprehended</hi> and receiued <hi>by Faith onely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Both</hi> the Sacraments, there bee <hi>two things</hi> to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered: there is an <hi>earthly Thing</hi> which we ſee and feele with our <hi>outward Senſes;</hi> and there is an <hi>heauenly and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all thing or grace,</hi> which wee <hi>cannot ſee,</hi> but by <hi>Faith. Both</hi> theſe <hi>parts</hi> are inſeparably v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited, and cannot be ſeparated one from another. He that is <hi>rightly fitted</hi> for the receiuing of the Sacrament, doth <hi>receiue both theſe parts together,</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:18943:31"/> the <hi>earthly</hi> with the <hi>heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and the <hi>heauenly</hi> with the <hi>earthly,</hi> which are ſo <hi>inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly</hi> conioyned by God (in a <hi>Sacramental vnion)</hi> that he that goeth about to ſeparate them, muſt needs <hi>run</hi> himſelfe vpon a <hi>curſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as wee are <hi>not</hi> to <hi>diuide</hi> and disioyne one part from an other, ſo wee muſt take heed, that we doe <hi>not confound</hi> them one with another, but keepe them <hi>diſtinct.</hi> As for example. We know that <hi>in the Perſon</hi> of our Sauiour Chriſt there are <hi>two ſeuerall Natures,</hi> viz. the <hi>God-head,</hi> and the <hi>Man-hood.</hi> The Nature of <hi>Man,</hi> is not the Nature of <hi>God;</hi> nor is the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>God,</hi> the Nature of <hi>Man.</hi> The <hi>one</hi> is not turned into the <hi>other;</hi> neither are they <hi>blended</hi> and <hi>mingled</hi> one Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18943:32"/> with the other; but both remaine <hi>distinct</hi> in the ſame perſon: yet are they ſo <hi>indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolubly vnited</hi> by <hi>perſonall vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on)</hi> that <hi>Death</hi> was not able to ſunder or ſeparate them. For howſoeuer <hi>(at the death of Christ)</hi> his <hi>Soule</hi> was ſeparated from his <hi>Body,</hi> and his <hi>Bodie</hi> ſundered from his <hi>Soule;</hi> yet euen <hi>when hee lay in the graue, both</hi> the parts of his Humane Nature, <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Soule,</hi> were as <hi>neerely</hi> vnited to his <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi> as they were at his <hi>Birth,</hi> or <hi>are now</hi> in heauen.</p>
               <p>So (to reſtraine my ſpeech to the Communion) There are <hi>two diſtinct</hi> and ſeuerall things in the Sacrament, an <hi>Earthly;</hi> as Bread and Wine: and an <hi>Heauenly; ſc.</hi> the Body and Blood of Chriſt. The <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> of Chriſt is not turned into
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18943:32"/> the <hi>Bread,</hi> neither is <hi>Bread</hi> tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into the body of Chriſt. Nor is the <hi>one</hi> blended or min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled with <hi>the other;</hi> but <hi>both</hi> remaine <hi>diſtinct</hi> in the <hi>ſame</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament: yet (though they be in themſelues diſtinct) they are ſo inſeperably conioyned together <hi>(by Sacramentall and myſticall vnion)</hi> that hee that doth receiue <hi>the one rightly,</hi> doth alſo <hi>neceſſarily</hi> receiue the <hi>other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as by <hi>vertue</hi> of the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonall vnion</hi> of the two natures in Chriſt, it commeth to paſſe that there is a <hi>Communication of</hi> properties; by reaſon where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of that which <hi>properly</hi> belongs to <hi>one</hi> Nature, is attributed to <hi>the other;</hi> as <hi>God is ſaid to bee Borne,</hi> and <hi>to dye:</hi> and <hi>the Son of Man is ſaid to bee in Heauen, when he was on Earth. God</hi> is <note place="margin">Iohn 3. 13.</note>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:18943:33"/> (by reaſon hereof) ſaid to bee <hi>Man;</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> to be <hi>God,</hi> and that <hi>really,</hi> and <hi>truly.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So, by <hi>vertue of</hi> the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall vnion,</hi> that is betwixt the <hi>hallowed Bread,</hi> and the <hi>Body</hi> of Chriſt in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: the <hi>Bread</hi> is truly called the <hi>Body</hi> of Chriſt, and the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> of Chriſt the <hi>Bread.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Fruite</hi> of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, is the <hi>participation of the Body and Blood of Chriſt.</hi> There is <hi>no one ſentence,</hi> of holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which ſaith that wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, by this Sacrament, bee made partakers of Chriſt his Body and Blood, except <hi>they</hi> be firſt <hi>materially conteined</hi> in the <hi>conſecrated Elements</hi> of Bread and Wine; or the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> be <hi>ſubſtantially</hi> chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, the one into the <hi>Body,</hi> the other into the <hi>Blood</hi> of Chriſt.
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18943:33"/> 
                  <hi>This is my body, This is my Blood;</hi> are words of <hi>Promiſe:</hi> we doe <hi>beleeue</hi> that God is <hi>faithfull</hi> and <hi>true</hi> of his word, and doth performe what hee doth promiſe; Albeit we doe not vnderſtand the <hi>manner how:</hi> nor dare <hi>preſcribe</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him the manner, <hi>which way</hi> he ſhall make it <hi>his Body</hi> to vs, either by <hi>Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ating</hi> or <hi>Conſubſtantiating</hi> it, or elſe we <hi>will not beleeue him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Still remember, that it is a <hi>Sacrament of Faith,</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> hath relation to a <hi>word of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe.</hi> The <hi>word</hi> of promiſe is: <hi>this is my Body. This word</hi> I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue to be <hi>true,</hi> becauſe <hi>God</hi> ſpake it, who cannot <hi>poſsibly lye. This promiſe</hi> I know cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely that <hi>God</hi> will <hi>performe,</hi> (in <hi>making it</hi> his Body <hi>to mee)</hi> becauſe God is <hi>faithfull</hi> in
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18943:34"/> performing his promiſe. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe I doe not know <hi>which way,</hi> or <hi>after what manner</hi> hee will, or doth performe it: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>he</hi> hath <hi>not ſhewed me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If I knew the <hi>manner how</hi> God did make it his Body, then the Sacrament were to me as matter <hi>rather of Reaſon</hi> and Knowledge, then a <hi>Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of Faith</hi> and beliefe: I <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue</hi> that Chriſt was concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in <hi>the wombe</hi> of <hi>Mary, a pure Virgin,</hi> which neuer knew Man: but if you aske me <hi>the manner how?</hi> I confeſſe, I <hi>know not:</hi> and if I <hi>knew</hi> the <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> how; then <hi>that Article</hi> of Chriſtes Conception, were to <hi>mee</hi> rather a matter of <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> then an <hi>Article of Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer, ſeeing theſe wordes (This is my Body) are
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:18943:34"/> 
                  <hi>words of Promiſe:</hi> and ſeeing that both <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans,</hi> and <hi>Papiſtes</hi> doe <hi>all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree,</hi> that <hi>by the Sacrament,</hi> Chriſt doth <hi>really</hi> and <hi>truely</hi> performe in vs his <hi>promiſe;</hi> what doth it profit vs to know whether he doth it by <hi>Conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiation,</hi> or <hi>Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or <hi>ſome other way,</hi> beſt knowne to himſelfe? which is a <hi>thing</hi> which can <hi>no wayes</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther further vs, or hinder vs, howſoeuer it ſtand.</p>
               <p>Therefore I aduiſe you to follow the counſell of a moſt iudicious, and excellent De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine, Maſter <hi>Hooker,</hi> who wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccl. Polit. Lib.</hi> 5.</note> you to take that wherein <hi>all ſides</hi> (both Proteſtants, and Papiſtes, and Lutherans) <hi>doe agree</hi> and conſent: and then conſider <hi>by it ſelfe,</hi> what cauſe there is, why <hi>the reſt in queſtion</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:18943:35"/> ſhould not rather be <hi>reiected</hi> as ſuperfluous, then <hi>vrged</hi> as ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary. It is on <hi>all ſides</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that the Sacrament is a <hi>True</hi> and <hi>Reall participation</hi> of Chriſt, who thereby im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth not onely <hi>Totum ſui,</hi> but <hi>Totum ſe, Himſelfe wholly,</hi> euen his whole entire perſon, as a <hi>Mysticall head</hi> vnto euery <hi>Soule</hi> that receiueth him: and that euery <hi>ſuch Receiuer</hi> doth <hi>incorporate</hi> or vnite himſelfe to Chriſt, as a <hi>Mysticall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> of him: yea, and as a <hi>fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low member</hi> of all true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Soules <hi>liuing</hi> on earth, or <hi>triumphing</hi> in heauen.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it is alſo agreed on; That to whom the <hi>Perſon of Chriſt</hi> is thus communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>to them</hi> he giueth (by the ſame Sacrament) <hi>his holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:18943:35"/> to ſanctifie <hi>them,</hi> as it ſanctifieth <hi>him which is their</hi> head.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it is likewiſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt; that what <hi>Merit, Force, Vertue</hi> or <hi>Efficacie,</hi> there is in the <hi>Sanctified Body and Blood</hi> of Chriſt, we doe <hi>freely, fully,</hi> and <hi>wholly</hi> receiue it by <hi>this Sacrament.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, all ſides ſay, that the <hi>effect</hi> thereof <hi>in vs,</hi> is a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al <hi>Tranſmutation</hi> of our Soules from <hi>ſinne</hi> to <hi>righteouſneſſe;</hi> from <hi>Death</hi> and corruption, to <hi>Immortalitie</hi> and Life.</p>
               <p>Fiftly, all ſides confeſſe, that becauſe the Sacrament (I meane the <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine)</hi> being, of <hi>it ſelfe,</hi> but a corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible and <hi>Earthly Creature,</hi> muſt needs be thought an <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely instrument,</hi> to worke ſo <hi>admirable effects</hi> in Man; wee
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18943:36"/> therefore are to <hi>reſt</hi> our ſelues vpon <hi>Gods Omnipotencie,</hi> vpon the ſtrength of his glorious and vnreſiſtable power, who <hi>is able</hi> and <hi>will</hi> bring to paſſe, that the <hi>Bread</hi> and the <hi>Cuppe</hi> which he giueth vs, ſhalbe <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and truly</hi> that thing <hi>which he promiſeth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is agreed on <hi>all ſides;</hi> and <hi>tbis is</hi> as much as is <hi>neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary</hi> to be knowne and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued touching our <hi>receiuing of Christ,</hi> in the Sacrament, to the comfort of our Soules.</p>
               <p>The ſecond <hi>thing</hi> to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in <hi>Faith,</hi> is <hi>Applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Therefore euery Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicant muſt not onely <hi>know,</hi> but <hi>apply</hi> that in <hi>particular</hi> to himſelfe, which hee <hi>beleeueth</hi> in <hi>generall:</hi> as that Chriſtes <hi>Body</hi> was crucified <hi>for him,</hi> and his <hi>Bloud</hi> ſhed <hi>for him.</hi>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:18943:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth it by his <hi>owne example, I liue,</hi> ſaith hee, <note place="margin">Galat. 2. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>by the faith of the Sonne of God, who hath loued mee, and hath giuen himſelfe for me.</hi> And this <hi>Application</hi> cannot bee better performed, then in <hi>Eating this Bread,</hi> and <hi>drinking this Cup:</hi> for ſo often as we eate this Bread, and drinke this Cup<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>we</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>doe Commemorate the Lordes Death. Euery Communion</hi> is as it were, a <hi>new Crucifixion</hi> of Chriſt. Chriſt was crucified <hi>at Hieruſalem:</hi> but Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tels the <hi>Galatians,</hi> that hee was crucified <hi>among them. Not</hi> that <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 1.</note> hee ſuffered death <hi>in Galatia;</hi> but becauſe <hi>of the Communion:</hi> which is a Commemoration and <hi>Repreſentation of the Death and Paſsion of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore when I kneele at the Lords Table (to the ende
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18943:37"/> that I more effectually apply Chriſt to mine owne Soule) I <hi>am to ſet my ſelfe</hi> as it were at the very <hi>foot of Chriſt his croſſe,</hi> and to conſider <hi>Him</hi> hanging there, enduring the vnknown wrath and curſe of God, and ſhedding his moſt precious blood <hi>for me,</hi> and <hi>for my ſinnes. That I was</hi> the cauſe, why <hi>Hee</hi> was <hi>wounded,</hi> rent, torne, and moſt ſhamefully vſed; That <hi>my ſinnes murdered</hi> the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and innocent <hi>Sonne of God;</hi> that he ſuffered <hi>nothing for his owne ſake,</hi> but all for <hi>mine:</hi> that he ſuſtained his <hi>Fathers wrath,</hi> to turne that wrath <hi>away</hi> from me; and to make <hi>God and mee friends:</hi> that hee was content to be made a <hi>Curſe</hi> to <hi>ſaue</hi> me from the curſe, and make mee <hi>bleſſed:</hi> that he ſuffered <hi>ſhame,</hi> to <hi>ſaue mee</hi> from ſhame, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18943:37"/> 
                  <hi>crowne</hi> mee with <hi>glorie, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>there</hi> (at the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Table) am I <hi>ſo</hi> to collect and <hi>gather vp my</hi> ſtragling thoughts, that <hi>(ſhutting out</hi> of my minde all other cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) I am ſo to ſettle my ſelfe, as if <hi>None</hi> were there preſent, but <hi>God the Father,</hi> and <hi>God the Sonne,</hi> and <hi>I my ſelfe. God</hi> the Father, who is the <hi>perſon offended: I,</hi> who am the <hi>offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor;</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who hangs on the Croſſe, as my <hi>Pawne</hi> and <hi>Suretie,</hi> to pay my <hi>Debt;</hi> ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>all that</hi> which is due <hi>vnto mee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And if I aske the reaſon, why <hi>God</hi> gaue his <hi>Sonne</hi> to doe and ſuffer <hi>all this</hi> for my ſake, or why the <hi>Son</hi> of God <hi>would</hi> ſuffer it? I ſhall finde <hi>none,</hi> but the great &amp; <hi>infinite loue</hi> to <hi>me,</hi> who deſerued no loue at all;
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:18943:38"/> but rather <hi>all hatred and ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi> from them.</p>
               <p>It was in God his incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible loue, that cauſed him to <hi>giue his</hi> Sonne <hi>to mee,</hi> and <hi>for mee. God ſo loued the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 3. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>world, that he gaue his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne, &amp;c. This loue</hi> of Gods, is a <hi>Sic</hi> without any <hi>Sicut;</hi> beyond all compariſon: nothing that euer was, or ſhall bee, may ſtand in compariſon with it. God <hi>ſo</hi> loued the world, that he gaue his onely begotten Sonne. It is as much (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine)</hi> as if ſome <hi>mightie Monarch,</hi> who had but <hi>one</hi> only <hi>Sonne,</hi> ſhould haue in his Kingdome a miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>poore Subiect,</hi> fallen into a deſperate diſeaſe, that were <hi>not curable</hi> by any meanes in the world, but <hi>by waſhing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in a Bath made of the bloud</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:18943:38"/> 
                  <hi>of the young Prince:</hi> And the <hi>King</hi> ſhould ſo farr tender the health of that <hi>poore Snake,</hi> that (hauing but <hi>one Sonne,</hi> and him the <hi>Hope</hi> of his poſteritie, and <hi>Heire</hi> of his Kingdome) hee ſhould cauſe <hi>all his</hi> veynes to bee opened, and all <hi>his bloud,</hi> euen to the very <hi>laſt drop,</hi> to be emptied out of his <hi>Sons bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> to the loſſe of his life; and all this, <hi>to ſaue the life of a meane fellow,</hi> of no parts, or deſerts at all. <hi>Such</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine) was the loue</hi> of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Father <hi>towards mee,</hi> the meaneſt of his ſubiects; hee gaue the <hi>life</hi> and <hi>blood</hi> of his onely <hi>deare Sonne,</hi> to cure and heale <hi>mee</hi> a miſerable <hi>wretch,</hi> that otherwiſe had neuer been cured.</p>
               <p>A fine and elegant <hi>Compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſon</hi> it is; but yet it commeth
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18943:39"/> ſhort of Gods loue. For the <hi>life</hi> of a <hi>Prince,</hi> (though it bee of a very <hi>high price,</hi> in ſo much that the people ſay to <hi>Dauid, Thou art worth ten thouſand of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>vs;)</hi> yet the <hi>life of the Sonne of God,</hi> is more worth then the liues of a thouſand millions of Princes. Beſides, the poo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſt <hi>man,</hi> nay the pooreſt <hi>gnat,</hi> in regard of the <hi>greatest</hi> Prince on the earth, is not ſo meane &amp; <hi>poore;</hi> as the <hi>greateſt</hi> Prince that euer was, is in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Gods onely begotten Sonne. So that <hi>no loue</hi> may bee compared to <hi>this loue</hi> of God, in giuing his Sonne <hi>for mee:</hi> except it be <hi>the loue of the Son</hi> who gaue <hi>himſelfe</hi> for me, and <hi>to me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God <hi>ſo</hi> loued <hi>mee,</hi> that in reſpect of <hi>mee,</hi> hee ſeemed <hi>not to loue</hi> his Sonne: the Sonne
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18943:39"/> 
                  <hi>ſo</hi> loued <hi>mee,</hi> that in reſpect of <hi>mee,</hi> he ſeemed <hi>not to loue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,</hi> but gaue away his <hi>owne life</hi> to ſaue <hi>my life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His death <hi>to me,</hi> is the death of mine <hi>High Prieſt;</hi> by it I am reſtored to my <hi>forfeited inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance in the heauenly Canaan.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Numb. 35. 28.</note> His <hi>life and blood</hi> to me, is the life and blood of the <hi>Pelican</hi> in the wilderneſſe; who dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth her <hi>owne breaſt,</hi> and ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth <note place="margin">Pſal. 102.</note> her blood vpon her yong that are ſtung <hi>with Serpents,</hi> to reſtore them to their <hi>health,</hi> though it bee with loſſe both of her <hi>blood</hi> &amp; <hi>life.</hi> His blood is <hi>to mee,</hi> not onely the <hi>blood of Remiſsion</hi> of ſinnes, in <hi>forgiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing;</hi> but <hi>in giuing</hi> vnto me, that which I could neuer haue pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed; it is <hi>Sanguis Teſtamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti,</hi> the Blood of the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; whereby Chriſt (as in
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18943:40"/> 
                  <hi>his Will and Teſtament)</hi> doeth giue and bequeath vnto me a <hi>Legacie</hi> or Heauen. <hi>His blood</hi> is the blood of <hi>Gods owne</hi> Son, the <hi>Heire</hi> of all things in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen and earth. I doe eate <hi>his fleſh,</hi> and <hi>drinke his blood,</hi> and by that am made (hauing the <hi>Blood royall</hi> within me) one of the <hi>blood royall,</hi> and <hi>Sonne</hi> and <hi>Heire</hi> of God, and ioynt-heire with Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beneficium poſtulat officium:</hi> Euery benefit doth challenge a dutie at mine hands. And <hi>what</hi> ſhall I render to the Lord for <hi>all theſe his</hi> benefits? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſaith <hi>Dauid, I will take the Cup of ſaluation,</hi> and call vpon the name of the Lord; that is, <note place="margin">Pſal. 116.</note> giue him thanks &amp; praiſe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>O my God, thou art good and true!</hi> O my ſoule, <hi>thou art bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and happy!</hi> And for this
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:18943:40"/> cauſe, this Sacrament of the Communion is called <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſtia:</hi> becauſe it is a <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Thankeſgiuing</hi> to God, for the vnſpeakeable benefites which we receiue at his hands, <hi>in</hi> and <hi>by</hi> the Sacrament.</p>
               <p>But wee muſt not giue him thanks &amp; praiſe with <hi>the mouth only;</hi> but to ſhew that our <hi>hearts</hi> are truly thankfull vnto him, we muſt ſtudy and endeauour to render <hi>loue for loue:</hi> for <hi>that is all</hi> that hee requires at our hands; <hi>Loue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is recorded by <hi>Xenophon,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 13. <hi>Poet. Cyr.</hi>
                  </note> that that potent and puiſſant <hi>King</hi> of the <hi>Perſians, Cyrus</hi> (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taken <hi>Tygranes, King</hi> of the <hi>Armenians</hi> captiue in war, and led him and his <hi>Queen</hi> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners to his owne Court) did vpon a day bid them to his <hi>own Table;</hi> and in a <hi>ſport</hi> and merri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18943:41"/> asked of <hi>Tygranes, How much he would bestow to ranſom his Queen?</hi> He preſently made anſwer, <hi>If I had that kingdome which thou haſt wonne from mee by the Sword, I would willingly part with that to redeeme her; and, if that were not enough, I would ſpend my life, and powre out my blood for her. Cyrus,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrangely taken with the conſideration of ſuch exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue meaſure of coniugal loue, yearned in compaſſion toward them, and reſtored them not onely to their <hi>libertie,</hi> but alſo to their <hi>kingdome.</hi> When <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granes</hi> was at home in his own <hi>Court,</hi> hee thus beſpake his wife the Queene: <hi>Lady, what doe you thinke of King</hi> Cyrus? <hi>Is not he a moſt vnmatchable &amp; Heroicall King? Is not hee onely worthy to weare the ſtile and title</hi>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:18943:41"/> 
                  <hi>of a King?</hi> The wiſe Ladie preſently made anſwer: <hi>Sir, I wot not what you ſay; neither can I remember what King</hi> Cyrus <hi>did ſay or doe, whereby I might take notice of his wiſedome and prudence: for all the while that I (with your ſelfe) remained a cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue in Perſia, I neuer caſt mine eyes vpon any one, but vpon him that was reſolued to ſet mee at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, with the loſſe and expenſe of his owne blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Behold here, a <hi>Leſſon</hi> taught you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this vertuous <hi>Queene:</hi> She acknowledged her ſelfe to be <hi>indebted</hi> to her husband <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granes,</hi> for that he was purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to <hi>ſpend his owne blood for her ranſome,</hi> that (for the <hi>vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency</hi> of loue and affection <hi>to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him)</hi> ſhee could not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure to look vpon <hi>any other</hi> in all the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Perſia,</hi> no, not
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:18943:42"/> vpon <hi>King Cyrus himſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How <hi>much</hi> then (dear Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> are you indebted to your <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Spouſe,</hi> ſeeing that he hath not only <hi>purpoſed</hi> to <hi>redeeme &amp; ranſome you</hi> with his <hi>owne deareſt blood;</hi> but <hi>hath</hi> powred it foorth <hi>indeed,</hi> euen vnto the laſt drop, hauing <hi>for your ſake,</hi> ſuffered ſo much ſhame, ſo many ſorrowes, ſo many torments, to free &amp; ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome <hi>you</hi> from a moſt <hi>cruell thraldome,</hi> not of the <hi>Perſian,</hi> but of <hi>Sathan;</hi> &amp; reſtored you to the free poſſeſſion, and iuſt right of a Celeſtiall kingdom? Can you then look vpon any, can you find in your hearts to <hi>bestow one thought</hi> vpon <hi>any</hi> in the whole court of this world, ſaue onely vpon your <hi>crucified Lord</hi> &amp; Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt? Caſt <hi>all</hi> your thoughts, <hi>all</hi>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:18943:42"/> your looks, <hi>all</hi> your loue vpon him; <hi>Videte &amp; palpate, guſtate, &amp; videte:</hi> behold him &amp; feele him, taſt and conſider him: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognize his <hi>loue to you,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne <hi>him loue</hi> againe; <hi>for if any man loue not the Lord Ieſus,</hi> let him be <hi>Anathema Maran-atha.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1. Cor. 16. 22.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now <hi>this</hi> our <hi>Loue</hi> cannot better be expreſſed, then by a <hi>ioyful acknowledgement</hi> of thoſe <hi>wonderfull benefits</hi> which wee receiue from Chriſt, when we do <hi>worthily</hi> Commnicate: and a <hi>dutifull obedience</hi> to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements. <note place="margin">Iohn 14. ver. 15. 21. 24.</note> The <hi>later hereof,</hi> is (in part) touched before: therefore I will in a word or two, touch vpon <hi>the former,</hi> which is the ſpiritual and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral ioy, wherwith we ſhould bee filled at the time of our Receiuing.</p>
               <p>For the time of Receiuing is
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18943:43"/> not a time of <hi>moody</hi> and <hi>melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly</hi> paſſion, but a time of <hi>mirth</hi> and <hi>ioy</hi> in the Lord. It is <hi>Sacrum conuiuium;</hi> At a <hi>banket</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">A Holy Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quet.</note> men ought to bee <hi>very merry.</hi> Our dutie then it is to <hi>Reioyce;</hi> only we are to take heed, that we do not reioice <hi>in ſin,</hi> which is <hi>againſt</hi> the Lord: but <hi>Reioyce in the Lord. Reioyce in the Lord</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Philip. 4. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>alwaies; and againe I ſay Reioyce.</hi> The <hi>Holy ghoſt</hi> by the Apoſtle doth not only <hi>permit</hi> and giue leaue to vs to make merry and <hi>reioyce,</hi> but doth <hi>alſo exhort</hi> vs vnto it. And not <hi>only</hi> to <hi>reioyce,</hi> but to <hi>reioyce againe.</hi> He would haue our hearts <hi>rauiſhed</hi> with a <hi>double</hi> ioy. <hi>One</hi> for the <hi>Soule,</hi> and <hi>another</hi> for the <hi>Body;</hi> but <hi>both</hi> in the Lord. So that, not only <hi>our Soules ſhould be ioyfull in the Lord, &amp; reioyce in his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,</hi> but alſo our <hi>very Bones</hi>
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:18943:43"/> ſhould ſay, <hi>Lord, who is like vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee?</hi> So that the <hi>bones which</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 51. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>God hath broken may reioyce.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 35. 9. 10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>And certainly we haue <hi>great reaſon</hi> to reioyce <hi>in God</hi> for his goodneſſe to vs. For at the Communion (by the <hi>hands of his Miniſter)</hi> he doth paſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you <hi>vnder Seale,</hi> his owne <hi>body and bloud;</hi> nay, his <hi>Whole-ſelfe,</hi> and whatſoeuer <hi>benefit</hi> he wrought for mans ſaluation: as the <hi>Remiſsion</hi> and pardon of all your ſinnes; the <hi>Redemption</hi> and deliuerance of all your ſoules and bodies <hi>from eternall puniſhment</hi> in Hell; <hi>Perfect Friendſhip,</hi> and <hi>Reconciliation</hi> with God; and an <hi>vndoubted right</hi> and title to the kingdom of Heauen, with all <hi>the ioyes</hi> and bleſſedneſſe thereof.</p>
               <p n="1">1 You would <hi>reioyce</hi> and be glad at the heart, if (being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18943:44"/> but a matter of <hi>twenty,</hi> or <hi>an hundred thouſand pounds,</hi> (and not knowing which way to pay it, or any <hi>farthing</hi> of it) you could find <hi>one</hi> ſo kind, and <hi>bountifull,</hi> as would pay it <hi>all</hi> for you: and not aske one far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing <hi>backe,</hi> but only your <hi>true Loue, and hearty Thankfulneſſe.</hi> Beloued, <hi>wee</hi> are <hi>all</hi> in <hi>debt.</hi> Our ſinnes are <hi>Debts</hi> to God: <note place="margin">Math. 18. 24.</note> and they are of ſo <hi>high a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> that all the <hi>thouſands</hi> and millions in the world are not able to ſatisfie God <hi>for one of them;</hi> and euery one <hi>of vs</hi> are <hi>in</hi> for <hi>millions</hi> of thouſands Chriſt comes, and brings a <hi>Quietus est,</hi> diſcharging vs freely of <hi>euery one</hi> of thoſe debts, and paſſeth it vnder <hi>ſeale</hi> in the Sacrament; and haue we not <hi>farre greater</hi> cauſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce for this, then for <hi>the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi>
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:18943:44"/> For his blood, is the <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11. 25.</note> bloud of Remiſsion of ſinnes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If any of you had offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>the Law</hi> in any heinous manner, and for that (being <hi>le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally</hi> adiudged to death) had the <hi>Halter</hi> about his <hi>neck,</hi> vpon the <hi>Gallowes,</hi> being ready to be <hi>turned off</hi> the Ladder; would it not glad his heart, to ſee one come from <hi>the King,</hi> with his <hi>Pardon</hi> vnder <hi>Seale,</hi> procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the <hi>Prince</hi> to acquit him from death? Verily <hi>all of vs</hi> (beſides the <hi>actual</hi> breaches of Gods Law committed by our ſelues) were <hi>non prius nati, quàm damnati,</hi> as Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith; No ſooner borne, then condemned, &amp; vnder the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death. The <hi>halter</hi> was about our necks, and we ready to bee <hi>turned off</hi> the Ladder; there was but a <hi>puffe</hi> of ayre, a
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:18943:45"/> ſmall blaſt of <hi>breath</hi> in our no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils, betwixt <hi>vs</hi> and <hi>Hell-fire,</hi> betwixt our temporary life, and endles tormenting death. The Miniſter comes <hi>to vs</hi> (at the Sacrament) with a <hi>Pardon</hi> from the <hi>King of Heauen,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured by the death of the <hi>Prince of our Saluation,</hi> Ieſus Chriſt, <hi>ſealed</hi> with his precious bloud: and haue not we <hi>iuster cauſe,</hi> thinke you, to <hi>reioyce</hi> for our deliuerance <hi>from Hell,</hi> then the <hi>Malefactor</hi> hath for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance from <hi>Tyburne?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 If our Soueraigne Lord the King were iuſtly fallen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hatred and <hi>enmity</hi> againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of vs, and ſhould <hi>bend him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi> and the <hi>ſtrength of all his Subiects,</hi> to bee reuenged on <hi>Him</hi> for his rebellions; what a pitifull taking would that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty be in? how glad would he be
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:18943:45"/> of <hi>any</hi> that would procure, and could aſſure him of the <hi>Kings fauour,</hi> and perfect reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vnto him? And were not all of vs by <hi>Nature, Filij irae?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 2. 3.</note> and by daily multiplication of rebellions againſt God, <hi>profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed enemies</hi> to God, and God enemy to vs? Our Sauiour by his death, wrought our <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>attonement,</hi> our perfect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation with God. <hi>When we were enemies, wee were recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>to God by the death of his Sonne.</hi> And, to aſſure our ſoules of this our peace and reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation with God, Chriſt by his Miniſter, <hi>in the</hi> Sacrament of his Body and Blood, doth <hi>paſſe it vnder Seale</hi> to euery particular worthy Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If, being not borne to <hi>any foot</hi> of land, his <hi>Maiestie</hi>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:18943:46"/> ſhould beſtow vpon any of you a whole <hi>Shire</hi> to be yours for euer; I know <hi>that perſon</hi> would thinke himſelfe an <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie man.</hi> But behold, the <hi>King of Heauen</hi> doeth aſſure euery <hi>worthy</hi> Communicant, not of a <hi>Shire,</hi> but of a moſt <hi>ſpacious, ample,</hi> and <hi>glorious Kingdome,</hi> to bee poſſeſſed and enioyed, not for the <hi>Euer</hi> of <hi>Time</hi> in this life, but for the <hi>Euer</hi> and <hi>Euer</hi> of eternitie: And haue wee not good cauſe to bee merry and ioyfull then? God is <hi>True and faithfull of his word and promiſe:</hi> and wee knowe that Hee by the Sacrament doth make <hi>euery true penitent Beleeuer</hi> as ſure of his eternall Kingdome; as <hi>any Prince</hi> (if hee ſuruiue) can bee <hi>ſure</hi> to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite his Fathers <hi>Crowne.</hi> For <hi>by it,</hi> wee are all made <hi>Heires</hi>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:18943:46"/> 
                  <hi>of God,</hi> and <hi>Ioynt-heires</hi> with <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 17. Heb. 1. 2.</note> Ieſus Chriſt, who is the Heire of all the world.</p>
               <p>So that, as I ſaid, <hi>wee</hi> haue <hi>all</hi> iuſt cauſe of mirth and ioy: and would to God, we could all bee ſo <hi>truely merry</hi> and <hi>ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> as wee ſhould bee, <hi>both in Body, and in Soule;</hi> that <hi>not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> our Soules <hi>may bee ioyfull in the Lord, and reioyce in his ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 35. 9. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>but that all our Bones may ſay, Lord, who is like vnto thee?</hi> Let vs therefore, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we receiue this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, bee merry <hi>a Gods Name:</hi> Let vs <hi>leape, reioyce,</hi> and <hi>exult</hi> for our Redemption and Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation wrought by Chriſt: but let vs not reioyce in <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetting and Drunkenneſſe, nor in Chambering and wantonneſſe,</hi> nor in painted <hi>Pride &amp; haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe.</hi> For this is not to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:18943:47"/> 
                  <hi>in the Lord,</hi> but <hi>against the Lord;</hi> this is not to bee merry <hi>in Gods Name,</hi> but <hi>in the Deuils name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for all theſe benefites whereby both our Bodies and Soules may <hi>thus iuſtly</hi> be raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed with Ioy, the Lord our God exacteth <hi>no great matter</hi> at our hands, but that which wee may pay without any <hi>Trouble or Dammage</hi> to our ſelues; and that is (as I ſayd before) our Loue to God <hi>for his owne ſake,</hi> Loue to our Neighbours, <hi>for Gods ſake.</hi> wee are to wiſh euery <hi>of them</hi> all good, and to <hi>performe</hi> it vnto them to the vttermoſt of our power: <hi>helping</hi> them in their neceſſities, and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing</hi> them the wrongs they haue done vs, <hi>Euen as God for Christ his ſake forgaue vs.</hi>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:18943:47"/> For <hi>they</hi> are all fleſh of <hi>Chriſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>his fleſh,</hi> and bone of <hi>Christ his bone:</hi> and <hi>whatſoeuer wee doe to any of theſe,</hi> (becauſe they are the myſticall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of Ieſus Chriſt) <hi>whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee good or bad,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Math. 25. 45.</note> 
                  <hi>Christ accounts as done to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
